95% of agentic projects fail.
>> The reason for that failure is likely
99% of engineers, programmers,
developers don't know how to actually
build agentic system. In the agentics
and AI space, there's a tendency for
people to build applications the way
they've always built them with
human-centric models, review cycles,
long drawn-out sprints, and different
traditional tactics that were optimized
for a world where we built slowly over
time and gradually. Now, we're in a
world where we can literally copy
anything anywhere at at a moment's
notice. Ultimately, this is the
empowerment of developers to do more
with less.
>> And a lot of the the kind of like ways
in which that can be done
um
in a
in a more predictable way, I guess, is
to use rails or guardrails. Um one of
the things that that came out of the
foundation, I believe, uh was Spark,
SPARC.
Um
talk us through a little bit about what
kind of was the driving force behind
Spark? Uh was it was it pain in terms
of, you know, seeing how people or
yourselves were being able to develop
code and what the different kind of
angle or perspectives you needed from
that cuz I know it's obviously very
specification-based, but there are also
a number of different things beyond just
specifications which are important to to
allow your agentic processes to build in
a predictable way.
>> Exactly. And what we saw, if you if you
rewind about a year and a half, we saw
that a lot of the early work within
these uh coding systems, but even before
agents became so popular, were limited
by the specification itself. And a lot
of the development was happening on a
kind of function by function basis. Fix
this, copy and paste this into the
system, and and as you said, a kind of
autocomplete, Which was fine and and I
that was a not a bad starting point. But
once we start looking at how do we
create larger, more complex applications
with interconnected relationships, data
structures, user experience components,
infrastructure, it be it became
important to create a specification that
the AI could follow, implement, test,
and verify. Now, part of that it was an
homage to some of the work I did 25
years ago with Sun Microsystems and
their Spark processor. I'm not going to
lie, it is Spark with a C. And and AI's
pretty good at creating acronyms and as
anyone can see the RUV stands for
something new every other day for me.
But ultimately the the specification
allowed for a kind of specification
that said, "Here's what I'm building." A
PRD if you will.
And then rather than building the entire
specification, what what I ended up
doing was saying, "I need to create a
pseudo code outline." So I'm not trying
to build the entire code. Obviously
that's going to happen in the later
stage. What I want to do is create a
scaffolding that allows the AI to
understand the general structure of what
the code needs to look like before it
implements it. So the second stage was
basically a kind of rudimentary
scaffolding of all the parts of the
application.
Then we then once we had that, then we
have a defined architecture. An
architecture that that would be defined
based on the code. Once we had that,
then we could go through a refinement
phase. That was the iteration. The
refinement provides a mechanism to say,
"Now we have a pseudo code outline and a
defined architecture which includes all
the various parts of the application.
Now we can start actually start building
that." The refinement turned out to be a
really interesting part when we got to
the point of a parallel or concurrent
development process. So now that we know
exactly all the parts of the
application, we can get different
different agents to work on different
parts of the overall application
independently of each other, although
connected through the architecture
itself,
using a test-driven development
approach,
which is the completion.
The test-driven development approach,
and I'm going to give you a quick
background for those that aren't
familiar with test-driven development,
there are essentially two different
approaches to test-driven development.
The traditional test-driven development
approach, sometimes referred to as the
Detroit school, which is essentially
creating the test as you create the
code, and that's what most test-driven
development today does. You have a
function or or part of an application,
you create a test, you write the code,
it passes and fails.
That was great for people, but it's not
great for autonomous agents building
things. The other approach was referred
to or is referred to as the London
school of test-driven development. Now,
the London school of test-driven
development uses a a scaffolding. It's
basically
developers hate it, because you're
basically creating the entire
application several times. One, you're
creating the entire in much like what I
defined in in the Spark architecture,
you're creating the outline of all the
parts and how all the parts work before
you ever build the application, then
you're building the application,
it fails, it always fails, then you're
going to then you're doing it again. So,
you're literally building that the
application at least three times,
possibly four times.
But, what's interesting about this
approach when you have AI agents is one,
they don't actually complain about
having to do the same work four times,
they they're AI, and and you're doing it
really really quickly and concurrently.
So, what would take months or many weeks
now can happen in an afternoon. And and
that and that provides again a guide for
the AI to follow, and once all those all
those tests pass, generally speaking,
assuming there's there it's not
completely simulated,
your application works. Now, different
languages work better than others. So,
there
a lot a lot of people ask, "What's the
optimal language for this?" Well, you
know, there's Python and there's you
know, Node and JavaScript and TypeScript
wrote like that, but the problem with
those languages is they're permissive,
meaning that these languages are allow
you to build with a lot of flaws and
they they'll they'll basically work even
if they're not right. And then you have
languages like Rust, which are very
explicit in in their definition,
deterministic. It's really hard to build
bad things in Rust because it just
doesn't work if it's if it's not built
correctly. So, by applying a rigid
specification to a
less permissive or rigid programming
language, the combination gives you the
ability to build really really
complicated, hard, broad projects and
basically know reliably that it'll work
when you're done.